<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A succinct philosophicall declaration of the nature of clymactericall yeeres, occasioned by the death of Queene Elizabeth. VVritten by T:VV</title>
            <author>Wright, Thomas, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26043.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855805</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855805</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21308</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15778)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21308)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1646:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A succinct philosophicall declaration of the nature of clymactericall yeeres, occasioned by the death of Queene Elizabeth. VVritten by T:VV</title>
                  <author>Wright, Thomas, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Valentine Sims] for Thomas Thorpe, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Crane, by Walter Burre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T:VV: = Thomas Wright.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A"; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part 2 of his: The passions of the minde: London, 1604.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original formerly in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (since deaccessioned).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603.</term>
               <term>Emotions --  Early works to 1850.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:1"/>
            <p>A Succinct Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall declaration of the nature of <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres, occaſioned by the death of Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(⸪)</p>
            <p>Written by T: W:</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Thorpe consisting of a boy with wings on his right arm and with his left hand holding or fastened to a weight, construed in the emblem tradition a talent kept from rising by the burden of poverty (McKerrow 142)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Thomas Thorpe, and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crane, by Walter Burre. 1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="philosophical_treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:2"/>
            <head>A Succinct Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall declaration of the nature of <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres, occaſioned by the death of Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the death of <hi>Queene</hi> ELIZABETH, who died in the 70. yeere of her age, which was the <hi>Clymactericall</hi> period of her life, diuerſe pregnant wits, and curious Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers were aſſembled by chance togither, &amp; among ſundry other learned Diſcourſes, one demaunded of me, what were theſe <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres, their nature, and effects: For (quoth hee) I haue heard many Philoſophors and Phiſitians talke of them, but as yet I neuer throughly could pierce or peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate them. I aunſwered him, that the Treatiſe thereof required longer time, then that place and preſent occaſions afforded, but that afterwards at more leyſure hee ſhould vnderſtand them, if hee were deſirous to learne: The Gentleman impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21308:3"/> me ſo much, as at laſt hee drew me to write this Diſcourſe which followeth: &amp; for that it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not altogether impertinent to this explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Paſſions, I thinke it not vnfit to be inſerted in the laſt Booke of the <hi>Paſsions</hi> of the <hi>Minde;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame temper of body, and propenſion to death, which is the baſe of <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeres; the very ſame conferres much, either to mooue Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or hinder the opperations of the ſoule, as in the progreſſe of this diſcourſe ſhal plainly appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clymax</hi> in Greeke ſignifieth a Staire or a Ladder, and metaphorically is applyed to the yeeres of a man or womans life; as if the whole courſe of our dayes were a certaine Ladder, compounded of ſo many ſteppes.</p>
            <p>True it is, that as the conſtitutions of mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are, for the moſt parte, of two ſortes, the one is firme and ſtrong, the other more weake and feeble: ſo the Phiſitians by long experience haue obſerued, that the fatall ends of them who be of a luſtie conſtitution, finiſh for moſt part in ſome ſcore of yeeres, and ſo they number ſuch perſons periods by twentie, 40. 60. 80. 100. 120. And to<note place="margin">Other count them by tens.</note> this purpoſe ſayde <hi>Moſes,</hi> *whoſe eyes were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther darkned, nor any tooth looſed. *<hi>Centum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginti</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 31. 2.</note> 
               <hi>annorum ſum hodie, non poſſum vltra egredi, &amp; ingridi:</hi> I am now an hundred and twenty yeeres old, I can no more goe out and come in, that is, no longer liue: and ſo it fell out, for that *ſame yeere<note place="margin">Deut. 34. 7.</note>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21308:3"/> he died. And GOD himſelfe ſaid of man *<hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>dies illius centum &amp; viginti anni.</hi> The dayes of man ſhall be an hundred and 20. yeeres.</p>
            <p>The next <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeere in them of ſolide and virile conſtitution is an 100, and ſo the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures report. <hi>Numerus dierum vitae hominum vt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 18. 8</note> 
               <hi>multum centum anni.</hi> The number of the dayes of the life of men at moſt is an 100 yeeres. Another kinde of men whoſe complexion is weaker, haue a leſſer kinde of meaſure, as they haue ſhorter life; and yet theſe alſo be of two ſorts, ſome ſtronger, ſome weaker: the firſt <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres are nine, eighteene, tweentie ſeauen, thirty ſix, forty fiue, fifty foure, ſixty three, ſeauenty two, eighty one; the ſeconds are, ſeauen, foureteene, twenty one, twenty eight, thirty fiue, forty twoo, forty nine, fifty ſix, ſixty three, ſeauenty. Of theſe two ages ſpake <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee ſayde. <hi>Dies annorum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 89. 10.</note> 
               <hi>nostrorum in ipſis ſeptuaginta anni. Siautem in poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus octoginta anni amplius eorum labor &amp; dolor.</hi> The dayes of our yeeres are ſeauentie yeeres, and if in Potentates they be eightie, the labour and griefe is greater.</p>
            <p>The moſt daungerous of all theſe paſſages or ſteps, are the forty nine, compounded vpon ſeuen times ſeauen: and ſixty three ſtanding vppon nine times ſeauen, and next to theſe is ſeauenty, which containeth tenne times ſeauen; they number them alſo by nine, and ſo make eighty one, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21308:4"/> moſt perillous as comprehending nine times nine.</p>
            <p>Theſe obſeruations then of Phiſitians preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as true, for men that are wiſe, vertuous, and experimented in their faculties ought to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued (for wiſdome and experience protect them from errour, and honeſtie from lying and deceite) it were good to examine and ſearch out the cauſe of theſe notable alterations and daungers of death in the <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres, for thoſe humors which alter the bodie, and diſpoſe it to ſickneſſe, and death; the ſame bend the ſoule to take inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affections and paſſions. I haue heard ſome Phiſitians reſolue this doubt into the influence of heauens, to wit, that ſo manie courſes of the Sunne, Moone, and Planets from the time of a mans Natiuitie, worke ſuch effects; ſo that ſome men, let them liue neuer ſo orderly, after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie circular motions of the Sunne and Moone haue warbled ouer their heads, vppon neceſſitie they muſt fall into one ſickneſſe or another, and ſo die.</p>
            <p>Some others ground this varietie and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous diuerſitie, vppon the ſingular prouidence of God, who hath created all thinges <hi>In numero, pondere &amp; menſura:</hi> and therefore hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed infallibly the periods of mens liues, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Pſalm: <hi>Notum fac mihi domine finem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: &amp; numerum dierum meorum quis eſt: vt ſciam
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21308:4"/> quid deſit mihi. Ecce menſurabiles poſuisti dies meos.</hi> Pſalme, 38. Make knowne vnto me O Lord mine end, and the number of my dayes, that I may knowe what I want. Loe thou haſt put my dayes menſurable, that is, preſcribed certaine bounds and limmits of age not paſſable: and therefore both Philoſophers and Phiſitians conclude, that a man with manie diſorders, ſurfeits, exerciſes, &amp;c. may ſhorten the natural courſe of his life, but that he cannot any way prolong it, &amp; paſſe the prefixed inſtant of his death: the ſimilitude we haue in a candle lighted, for let a man vſe all the diligence poſſible, the light and fire feeding vpon the candle, perforce will conſume it at laſt; and God or any Angell behoulding the quantitie of the wike, tallow, time of the yeere (for in cold weather a candle conſumeth more then in hote, <hi>Per antipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristaſin</hi>) and other circumſtances may preciſely foretell, that ſuch a candle cannot continue bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning longer then ſuch a minute of ſuch an houre; in a ſhorter time it may be conſumed with wind, witches, ſnuffe-fallings, or ſuch like things which waſte it away, but longer it cannot be prolonged: after the ſame ſort ſtandeth the courſes and the liſtes of our liues preſcribed by God and prefixed by nature: and ſo God hath appointed theſe Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie, and Nonarie yeeres as beſt ſeeming his wiſdome and prouidence.</p>
            <p>Theſe manners of declaration I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute, for albeit I doe thinke them both in ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21308:5"/> things moſt true, yet they are too generall and remote to anſwere and ſatisfie fully our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund. The difficultie, no doubt, is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, and rather I belieue it to be true for the authoritie of Phyſitians, then for any credite I can giue to theyr reaſons; for indeede all that I haue heard diſcourſe thereupon (and I haue heard ſome verie fine wits) and what I haue read, dooth not content nor ſatisfie my minde. Therefore I will ſet downe my Phyloſophicall conceite (for in this ſpeculation Phyſick dependeth vppon Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie) and firſt ſuppoſe that cuſtomes, habites, changes, and great alterations in mens bodies come ſeldome vppon a ſuddaine, but by little and little grow and increaſe by tract of time; and as we ſay.
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Gutta cauat lapidem, non vi ſed ſepe cadendo,</l>
                  <l>Sic homo fit doctus, non vi, ſed ſepe legendo.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The dribling drops by falling oft,</l>
                  <l>Not might, make marbles thinne:</l>
                  <l>So men by oft peruſing bookes,</l>
                  <l>Not force, doe learning win.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen</hi> to declare the nature and force of cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome<note place="margin">Galen. de Conſuet. c. 2.</note> and what effects it worketh in vs, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this queſtion: how it commeth to paſſe, that ſome mens natures abhor exceedingly ſome ſorts
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21308:5"/> of meate, and are not able to diſgueſt them; as for example, ſaith he, ſome cannot abide beefe, others ſhell fiſhes; and we haue manie who cannot ſo much as endure the ſight of cheeſe, others of aples: And yet theſe ſame perſons by little and little are brought to eate, diſgueſt, yea and greatly to like them? He anſwereth, that all beaſts and men haue naturall propenſions, to ſuch meates as are conſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the naturall proprieties of theyr bodies, and abhor ſuch things as are contrarie; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lyon feedeth vppon fleſh, not vpon hay; and the Oxe vpon hay not vpon fleſh; yet it falleth out that by tract of time, thoſe meates which we deteſted, after by vſe become familiar, for they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the body, and by the ſucke of theyr nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, change the affections and qualities of the ſtomack, in ſuch ſort, as that meate, which before was moleſtfull, and in very deede hurtfull, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſauorie and healthfull: and this he proueth, not onely to be true in men and beaſts, but alſo in ſeedes and trees, whoſe fruite in ſome countries are poyſon, transferred into other ſoyles where they receiue another kind of noriſhment, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, not only by tract of time; not hurtfull, but very healthfull; not poyſonfull, but pleaſant.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is to be conſidered, that our bodies generally haue certaine courſes, paſſages, ſtations or periods, wherein they notably change their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and operations: till 21. yeeres, or 25. at the moſt, we grow in height, for ſome come to theyr
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21308:6"/> full growth ſooner, ſome later: from 25. to fortie two, or forty fiue, we grow in breadth or thicknes, from this, till the end of our dayes we decline: the cauſe of theſe three notorious alterations is our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall beate or <hi>humidum radicale,</hi> (which in mine opinion is nothing els but the vitall temper, and qualification of euery ſolid part of our bodies) the which reſiding in a moiſt body, cauſeth it to grow, like the heate in a loafe of Dowe ſet in the Ouen: afterwards, what with internall heate, externall drying of the windes, and ſunne, and other conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall exerciſes, which daily exſiccate the body, &amp; draw out the vndegueſted moyſture, the innated heate is not able to rouze vp the body any more in height, but ſpreadeth it abroade, and ſo enlargeth, and ingroſſeth it: after which continuall working, heate is weakened, and ſo by little and little ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayeth: and finally reſolueth in diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in this ſeptuarie number of our yeeres, although we cannot diſcouer ſuch notorious dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, as in the three former paſſages, yet in theſe likewiſe, we may obſerue ſome markable change. At the firſt ſeauenth yeere, men commonly note, that then the child beginneth, to haue ſome little ſparkes of reaſon: and for this cauſe, the Cannon Law permitteth ſuch, directed by their parents or Tutors, <hi>contrahere ſponſalia,</hi> to make a promiſe of future mariage. In the foureteene yeere, the youth is thought to haue the perfit vſe of reaſon, &amp; then the Cannons account him capable of marriage.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21308:6"/> At twenty one, a man is reputed able iudiciouſly to diſpoſe of his goods, and faculties, and therfore the Common-law riddeth him then of his vvard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the Cannons giue him leaue to take the order of ſubdeacon: the firſt ſeauen yeeres are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>infantia,</hi> the ſecond <hi>pueritia,</hi> the third <hi>adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> the fourth, that is, from twenty one to twenty eight, <hi>iuuentus,</hi> from thence to forty nine, hee is eſteemed to ſtand <hi>in ſtatu virili,</hi> the next till ſixtie three is <hi>ſenectus,</hi> after, till ſeauenty &amp; ſeauentie ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for moſt part enſueth <hi>decrepita aetas.</hi> In all theſe periods, or <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres, it is to be noted, that although the change in that yeere be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued moſt palpably, and ſenſibly, yet in all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, they were preparing, working, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſpoſing there-vnto: as for example, wee muſt not thinke that the leaſt drop of rayne, which in effect breaketh the ſtone, dooth it of it ſelfe, for that were impoſſible, but it doth it in vertue, and by force and working of all the former: And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for this cauſe they were called <hi>anni ſcalares,</hi> for that euery yeere precedent, was a ſteppe to the laſt, wherein the Ladder or ſtaires were ended.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, there is a great diſpute among Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, what ſhould be the cauſe of the Paroxiſme<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or fittes in Agues, and once I my ſelfe being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a tertian Ague, in <hi>Italie,</hi> in the Cittie of <hi>Como,</hi> there came two Phiſitians my deere friends, and a Doctor of Diuinitie all at one time to viſite me, and euen then I ſtood in expectation of my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21308:7"/> fit. After many complements &amp; diſcourſes about my ſicknes, at laſt I demaunded theſe two Doctors of Phiſicke, that they would reſolue mee in one doubt about my diſeaſe: they aunſwered, with a good will: Well, ſayd I, you both conclude, and it ſtands with good reaſon, that this ſicknes of mine proceedeth from exceſſe of choller: now I would know of you, when my fit is paſt, is the choller all diſgueſted, conſumed, and voyded away or no? If it be conſumed, why dooth my Ague returne? if it be not conſumed, why dooth mine Ague de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part? The Phiſitians here aunſwered one contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to another: for the firſt ſayd it was diſgueſted: Why then returneth mine Ague? For this cauſe quoth he, the Ague proceedeth not onely of chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, but of choller putrified, corrupted, and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned. Now ſir, the choller poyſoned is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but other choller which remaineth, is not corrupted, but by the next paroxiſme it will be corrupted: Well, ſayd I, what thing is that which corrupteth &amp; poiſoneth that good choller, which before was not corrupted? It ſeemeth ſtrange to me, how ſo much preciſely ſhould be corrupted, and the other beeing ſo neere lying by it, or rather vnited with it, yea mingled in it, not to be infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: In truth I remember not what he aunſwered, but I am ſure he ſatisfied none of vs all. The other Doctor of Phiſicke ſayd, it was not conſumed, but nature feeling the force of that poyſon, vnited her ſelfe to fight againſt it, and ſo allayed moſt of the vehemencie, vigour, and malignitie thereof: and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21308:7"/> hee gaue an example of a pot of water ſet on the fire, for quoth hee, if the coales be couered with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, the hote water cooleth, blow the fire and it warmeth and boyleth, let aſhes returne, or the fire die, the water returneth to the firſt coldneſſe: So quoth hee, the poyſon of the choller, by natures might is ouercome, when the Ague departeth, but after that thoſe ſpirits and forces, which nature had vnited, are diſperſed, the fire is quenched, and choller againe corrupted. But quoth the other Phiſitian, ſo the ſickneſſe ſhould neuer depart, for if your choller be ſtill in cooling and heating, and nature now fighting, now ceaſing, when I pray you ſhall this combat be finally ended? Marry ſir quoth his fellow Doctor, in this ſort, nature mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateth the forces of choller this fit, and allayeth them: now nature in the meane time, is ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with good foode, and the humour either pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or quailed with phiſicke, and ſo by little and little it is quite diſgueſted.</p>
            <p>Not ſo ſaid the other, for then the ſecond fit ſhould alwayes be leſſe then the firſt, and the third leſſe then the ſecond, and ſo forward to the laſt: but this is falſe, for his third and fourth fits, were much more vehement, then either the firſt or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. And beſides, by this declaration, no man ſhould euer die vpon an Ague. For if in euery fit, the ſickneſſe ceaſſed not, vntill the humour were allayed, then certainly in Agues, (which are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21308:8"/> the fitte ſhoulde neuer paſſe, which is moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>With this the Doctor of Diuinitie, who was a very good Philoſopher, and for that he had beene much troubled with maladies, he was like manie wrangling Gentlemen, a petty-fogging Phiſitian at his owne coſts, as they be petty-fogging Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers thorow theyrowne ſutes. Why ſaid the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, may we not hold that the Ague is in the liuer and hart? No quoth the Phiſitians both, that can not be, becauſe no Phiſitian euer held, that any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue was <hi>in partibus ſolidis,</hi> that is, in the hart &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp;c. except the <hi>Hecticke.</hi> Well ſaid the diuine, I ſay not that it is in the hart and liuer immediatly, for that I will confeſſe perforce muſt be choller, but I ſay the fountaine and ſpring, the roote and origen to reſide in the liuer, the which immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſeth corrupted blood and inflamed choller, for they beeing extraordinarily corrupted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with vehement heate, cannot but engender blood, ſpirits, and humors of like infection and corruption. And by this way I aunſwere the firſt doubt: that when the Ague eaſeth, choller is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſted: Why then returneth it againe? Marie ſir, becauſe the hart and liuer beeing out of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in that ſpace of time engender ſo many more peruerſe humors, as oppreſſe nature, ſo vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and dangerouſly, that ſhee muſt imploy all her might to reſiſt them, abate them, extinguiſh them. In truth Maiſter Doctor (ſaid I) this opinion I like
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21308:8"/> very well, and I will confirme it, for ſince mine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue firſt beganne, theſe Phiſitians haue inculcated nothing ſo much vnto me, by word and deede, as to coole my liuer: to this effect all their ſyrrops and waters of Endiue, Sicory, and Barley tended. And with this diſcourſe wee ended our diſpute, &amp; mine Ague: the which with this pleaſant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference paſſed away.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>Plato</hi> auoucheth, that Agues haue ages<note place="margin">Plato in Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. de Natur.</note> like men, as alſo conſummations and ends, vvith whom <hi>Galen</hi> conſenteth: This ſentence of <hi>Plato, Valeſius</hi> a worthy Phiſitian explicateth in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. As there are two ſorts of diſeaſes, ſharpe and<note place="margin">Valeſius de Sacra Philo. cap. 7.</note> cronicall, both which haue theyr decretory daies, but not alike, for the ſharpe haue odde dayes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeauen: the cronicall twenty, ſixty, eightie, a hundred: ſo there are two prerogations or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of life: the one is common to many, the other to fewe, and ſuch as are of a moſt liuely conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: both of them haue theyr <hi>Clymactericall</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretory yeeres. The firſt wee number by ſeauen and nine, the latter wee count by tenne, and the laſt period is a hundred and twenty.</p>
            <p>To this Diſcourſe of <hi>Valeſius</hi> lette vs adde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne poynt of experience and doctrine of <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen. lib. 1. de diebus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretorijs c. 12.</note> who in the decretorie dayes of a feuer, which numbreth by ſeauen ſpecially, he will tell you the fourth day, whether the Agew will leaue the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient the ſeauenth, or whether hee ſhall die vpon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21308:9"/> the ſeauenth day, or no: and alſo withall, hee teacheth to foretell the very houre of death vppon the ſeauenth day.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, out of theſe conſiderations we may gather as much as will ſufficiently (I hope) ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Queſtion propoſed in the beginning of this Section, <hi>viz:</hi> why in theſe <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeeres men commonly die? To which I doe aunſwere, That for euery ſixe yeeres or eight, men ſtill ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vppe more or leſſe humours, which prepare the way for an Agew in the ſeauen or nine: As wee ſayde before, when the fitte is paſt, the heart and liuer prepare humours for the next enſuing, and in caſe they be not ſufficient in the ſeauen, they multiply to the nine; if in this they faile, then they paſſe to the foureteene, then to eighteene, &amp;c. And for this cauſe Phyſitians councell theyr Patients to purge in the Spring and Authumne, to hinder the increaſe of humours, albeit they feele themſelues nothing diſeaſed at all.</p>
            <p>This we may declare by the example of them, who are infected with hereditary diſeaſes, as the gowte, or the ſtone: for albeit they euidently appeere not till olde age, yet in all the progreſſe of their yeeres, the partes and humours inſenſibly are prepared. Or wee may ſay, that in ſixe or eight yeeres the liuer and heart which are foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of bloud, and origens of humours are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and corrupted, that in the laſt yeere they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21308:9"/> engender more vnnaturall ſuperfluous humours, than can ſtand with the right and naturall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the body.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, by this opinion a man ſhould euer be ſicke, for hee ſhoulde neuer want corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humours, wherein ſickeneſſe conſiſteth. To this I anſwere; firſt, that health conſiſteth not <hi>in indiuiſibili,</hi> in an indiuiſible poynt, ſo that it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth not ſome few peccant humours withall, but hath a certaine amplitude, like as if into a But of ſtrong Canary Wine, a man euery moneth ſhoulde put in halfe a pinte of water, euery day a ſpoonefull, at the moneths end, yea the yeeres end, the Wine woulde be almoſt as potent, as at the firſt, yea and perhaps more, if it bee well hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee ſee that Cuſtome breedeth qualities and alterations ſo inſenſibly, as in long time (till they come to a full growth) they can hardly be perceiued.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I doubt not but hee that hath for example the firſt foureteene yeere of his life for his <hi>Clymactericall,</hi> in the precedent yeeres, ſhall gather more corrupted humoures, then hee whoſe <hi>Clymactericall</hi> yeere is nine and fortie, and alſo feele himſelfe proportionally more weake, albeit hee can not well perceiue; for I my ſelfe haue knowne a man, almoſt with halfe his lungs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21308:10"/> rotten with a conſumption, and yet boldelie auowch that he was ſtrong, for <hi>Ab aſsuetis non fit paſsio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some will obiect, that wee ſee by experience many menne die within the ſpace of a day or two, who before were as ſound and whole, as coulde be: neyther in their vrine, blood, or pulſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any ſigne of ſickeneſſe, or ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
            <p>To this I aunſwere, that ſuch a man was ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppreſſed with ſome vehement Paſſion, or ſome violent exerciſe, or ſome other extrinſecall cauſe, which accelerated, peruerted, and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily augmented the humour, and ſo cauſed death: for as I ſaide aboue, although a man (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the common courſe of his dayes) can not paſſe his prefixed time and <hi>Clymactericall</hi> periode, yet by many meanes he may ſhorten it.</p>
            <p>Much more I coulde ſay, <hi>prò</hi> and <hi>contrà,</hi> for this Declaration, but becauſe it were ſomething too Phyſicall, and not ſo neceſſarie for this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Treatiſe, therefore I will bury it with ſilence: for this poynt, in very trueth, is ſo intricate, that I perceiue, the beſt wittes are exceedingly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to extricate themſelues out of it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21308:10"/>
            <p>And therefore, as this I eſteeme probable, ſo I woulde giue any Phyſitian moſt hearty thankes, who in few woordes woulde teach mee a better way.</p>
            <p>I ſayde in briefe, for I haue ſeene ſome ſuch long tedious Diſcourſes, as I loathed to peruſe them, doubting leſt the vncertaine profit, would not repay the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine payne.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21308:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
